In this video, I'll say a little about
using the course evaluation rubric.
The most common use of an evaluation
rubric is to achieve uniformity in grades
when a team of experts is grading
a large collection of examinations.
The goal is to assign a reliable
grade to each candidate's work.
In particular,
it's assumed that the people doing
the evaluation are experienced graders.
In this class, we're using
a rubric in a very different way.
Not to help experts produce
a reliable grade of a piece of work,
but as a mechanism to help
beginners learn about proofs.
If you look at the rubric for the course,
you see that it asks you to consider
five different features of proofs.
Logical correctness, clarity,
opening, stating the conclusion and
reasons.
I'll come to the sixth category later,
by the way.
These are all important
features of proofs.
And for pedagogic reasons,
are given equal weight.
Here's why.
As I state repeatedly
throughout the course,
proofs do much more than simply
establish that some statement is true.
Actually, in practice they don't really
do that, they simply provide evidence
that convinces a reasonable person
with sufficient background knowledge.
But let's leave that issue for now.
If you look at the role played
by proofs in mathematics,
you discover that just as
important as logical correctness
is the understandability of
the proof by an intended reader.
In fact, in practical terms
understandability is more important than
logical correctness.
There's probably no modern
proof of more than a few pages
that does not initially have
a logical flow buried somewhere.
What makes proofs useful is that
others can not only detect errors, but
also have enough information
to try to correct them.
Proofs are as much about
communication as establishing truth.
Because we have to use simple examples
to develop proof evaluation skills,
in most of the examples you see, one or
more of the rubric criteria will apply
only in a simplistic way if at all.
But in more complicated examples
they will all be important.
That's why the five criteria
carry equal weight.
When you evaluate arguments,
you should view them in terms of
each of the five rubric criteria
in turn on an equal footing.
True, experts rarely use rubrics.
They're so familiar with the proof
concept that they automatically and
holistically judge in terms
of all those perspectives.
For a beginner, the rubric breaks up
the task of judging the overall quality of
a proof to judging those
five aspects in turn.
Each of those five is considerably
simpler to do than the entire task,
but you'll still find it difficult.
After you've judged a proof in terms of
the five proof characteristics, the rubric
asks you to bring them all together to
produce a single grade for the proof.
This is the number you would enter
if your task were to assign a single
numerical grade to someone's proof.
It corresponds to the number an expert
working without a rubric would assign.
The rubric is designed to assist you as
a beginner to arrive at that final grade.
Incidentally, when you're evaluating
the work of another student,
as you would in test flight if you do it.
You do owe it to that student to be
as fair and accurate as possible.
But no one expects accuracy from someone
who is just beginning to learn about
proofs.
Because everyone's work is
evaluated by three fellow students,
all anonymously by the way, with
a reported grade computed from those three
grades, plus the individual's
own self grade.
It turns out that most of the time,
the final grade is pretty good.
Nevertheless, the real purpose of
the test flight evaluation process
is that it offers tremendous
benefits to the evaluator
in coming to a better appreciation
of what makes a good proof.
In simple terms, in this course,
the grading is primarily for
the benefit of the grader.